<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-common SYSTEM "../../libs-common/xubuntu-common.ent">
%xubuntu-common;
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-contributor SYSTEM "../libs/xubuntu-contributor.ent">
%xubuntu-contributor;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs-common/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
<!ENTITY language "C">
]>
<section id="docs-tasks">
	<title>Tasks</title>

	<section id="docs-tasks-user">
		<title>User documentation</title>

		<para>The documentation team works with the developers to ensure any new features that are part of the core functionality of the operating system are covered in the documentation. In addition, the documentation team makes sure features highlighted in the installer slideshow or any other marketing material are appropriately documented. When completely new sections are written, the documentation team makes sure the Xubuntu team has a chance to review and propose changes and fixes to the new sections. When any documented features are removed or changed, the team makes sure the documentation does not refer to any removed functionality.</para>

		<note><para>The team should be aware of changes to new releases, particularly on LTS releases and potential SRUs, as those might affect documentation.</para></note>

		<para>The documentation team is responsible for making sure the documentation is updated before the Documentation String Freeze prior to uploading. Once the upload is done, the team coordinates translation efforts and makes sure the documentation gets another upload before the Translation Freeze. The team should also request the <ulink url="http://docs.xubuntu.org/">online documentation</ulink> to be updated shortly before the release.</para>

		<para>The documentation team should also look to improve and expand the existing documentation, especially during the development cycles when most uploads are done for maintenance purposes. The team should involve the community in these efforts the best way they see fit.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="docs-tasks-contributor">
		<title>Contributor documentation</title>

		<para>The documentation team lead the efforts to write the contributor documentation. While the various subteams are responsible for their own sections, the documentation team should help the teams to get their content pushed to the main branch and where needed, help contributors to format the content in the DocBook markup.</para>

		<para>The <ulink url="http://docs.xubuntu.org/contributors/">online contributor documentation</ulink> should be kept updated especially when major changes are made; the documentation team should request an update whenever they see fit.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="docs-tasks-other">
		<title>Other tasks</title>

		<para>In addition to the above, the documentation team is strongly encouraged to do the following:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Work with the Quality Assurance team to write and maintain testcases</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Work with the website team to improve the website content and write FAQ or other documentation related articles</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Work with the marketing team on various projects, like flyers</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
</section>