<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-common SYSTEM "../../libs-common/xubuntu-common.ent">
%xubuntu-common;
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-contributor SYSTEM "../libs/xubuntu-contributor.ent">
%xubuntu-contributor;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs-common/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
<!ENTITY language "C">
]>
<chapter id="qa">
	<title>Quality Assurance (QA)</title>

	<note><para>There are various QA trackers, wiki and Launchpad pages, the links to which can be found on <xref linkend="qa-team-links" />.</para></note>

	<para>The Xubuntu QA team was formed to ensure that the quality of a released Xubuntu conforms to the parameters laid out in the Xubuntu Processes documents. In order to successfully accomplish this, close team working relationships, especially with the development team and the Xubuntu Council are paramount. Xubuntu's success is based on close working amongst all of its various teams.</para>

	<para>In addition, the team gives people contributing through testing of Xubuntu the opportunity to become part of the <ulink url="https://launchpad.net/~xubuntu-team">Xubuntu Team</ulink>. For that to be of practical use, the QA team should keep an eye on testing reports on the trackers and propose users they have seen taking a keen interest in the work of the QA team.</para>

	<para>Excluding testing itself, control of the testcases that we use for ISO and Package testing, along with communicating the testing requirements for any particular development cycle (hereafter cycle) to the community, makes up the bulk of the teams work in any given cycle.</para>

	<para>Members of the QA team should check the current Xubuntu QA blueprint, and assign themselves to tasks they feel able to undertake.</para>

	<section id="qa-team-testing">
		<title>Testing</title>

		<para>At the start of a cycle, the Release Team will discuss which ISO Testing Weeks we will participate in. Then, during a Community Meeting, members of Xubuntu Team will discuss and then ratify Xubuntu's participation during the cycle.</para>

		<para>Along with general testing of our OS, dealt with further in <xref linkend="qa-testing-exploratory" /> and <xref linkend="qa-testing-ppa" />, further responsibilities lie with ensuring that:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Sufficient testing takes place during ISO Testing Weeks</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Sufficient package testing takes place following calls to testers</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Sufficient testing has taken place by Final Release</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Bugs reported to our trackers are confirmed, or where unable to confirm, further information is requested from the reporter</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Where appropriate, confirmation of bugs can be asked of members of Xubuntu Team in the team devel IRC channel</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>Members of the QA team might find it useful subscribing to the <ulink url="https://launchpad.net/~xubuntu-bugs">Xubuntu Bugs</ulink> team in order to be aware of bugs being reported by users.</para>

		<xi:include href="qa-infra.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
		<xi:include href="qa-testing.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
		<xi:include href="qa-bugs.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
	</section>

	<section id="qa-team-trackers">
		<title>Working with trackers</title>

		<para>The initial decisions on what and when to test, will be taken following discussion with the members of the <ulink url="https://launchpad.net/~xubuntu-release">Xubuntu Release</ulink> team.</para>

		<para>At the start of a cycle, the QA team needs to ensure that:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Image testcases we use are still correct.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>When the intention is that package testing will take place during the cycle, package testcases required during the cycle are still correct.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>The testsuites on the Package Tracker make sense for what we intend to test during the cycle. Differences between regular and LTS releases are often, but not always, needed.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Scheduling of ISO, and when appropriate Package, testing should take place amongst the QA team.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>When there are changes to a package we test, following for example a bug fix, a further check of the testcase involved should take place. Further testing calls for that package should be made to check for regression during the cycle.</para>

		<para>When a package during test constantly fails, or bug reports indicate a failure in a package for something not tested, the testcase for that package can be disabled temporarily. The QA Lead is responsible for ensuring tests are both disabled and re-enabled when appropriate.</para>

		<para>Xubuntu ISOs are built and added to the tracker at approximately 02:00 UTC. This time can be changed by amending our build times on the <ulink url="http://bazaar.launchpad.net/~ubuntu-cdimage/ubuntu-cdimage/mainline/files/head:/etc/">ubuntu-cdimage crontab</ulink> and proposing the change.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="qa-team-testcases">
		<title>Working with testcases</title>

		<para>Information on the basic method of working with testcases can be found at the Ubuntu QA Team <ulink url="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/QATeam/ContributingTestcases/Manual">Manual Testcases</ulink> page.</para>

		<para><emphasis>We</emphasis> are only concerned with a specific set of tasks: grabbing the branch, making edits and then pushing the changes we need to the main branch. We have people in the Testcase Admin team for the LP Testcases, in addition any member of our Release Team can edit the tracker, this helps ensure that changes are moved through to the trackers quickly.</para>

		<para>To edit a testcase:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><ulink url="https://bugs.launchpad.net/ubuntu-manual-tests/+filebug">Report</ulink> the required change as a bug against the testcase project</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Assign yourself to the bug</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Create a local branch: <userinput>bzr branch lp:ubuntu-manual-tests</userinput></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Make changes to the testcase in your local branch</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Commit the changes: <userinput>bzr commit -m "Fix LP bug #BUGNO."</userinput></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Push to a personal remote branch: <userinput>bzr push lp:~username/ubuntu-manual-tests/bug-BUGNO</userinput></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>Once pushed to a personal remote branch, propose the change for merging - <xref linkend="bzr-merge-proposal" />.</para>

		<para>Respond to any requests for changes when asked by the Testcase Admins in order to get the required change through in a timely manner.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="qa-team-communication">
		<title>Communicating with Testers and Users</title>

		<para>While we have two sets of people in the community that we contact about required testing, Testers will get regular contact from us, but we should only, in general, call on Users at later stages.</para>

		<para>The QA Lead will be an administrator on the Testers Launchpad page and can contact those users via LP. Copies of testing calls sent to the devel mailing list should go to this group each time.</para>

		<para>Any member of the QA team can:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Mail the devel list with a testing call</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Just prior to an upcoming ISO testing week call, warn on the devel list</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Make an ISO testing week call</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>Xubuntu Users will be contacted for ISO testing at the Final Beta ISO Milestone.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="qa-team-release">
		<title>Release Responsibilities</title>

		<para>Much of the responsibility for the QA team at any release lies with the QA Lead.</para>

		<para>However, <emphasis>any</emphasis> member of the QA team can:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Work with the testing wiki <ulink url="https://wiki.xubuntu.org/releases/18.10/release-notes">Release Note</ulink></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Check status of bugs listed on the above draft</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Check status of work items on the QA blueprint, marking as appropriate</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>

	<section id="qa-team-post-release">
		<title>Post Release Tasks</title>

		<para>Following release, there are a few tasks that need to be done before the next release cycle begins.</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			 <listitem><para>QA Lead should set up the blueprints for both the QA team and the Bugs that the whole team uses</para></listitem>
			 <listitem><para>Check that the draft Release Note is up to date</para></listitem>
	 	</itemizedlist>
	</section>
</chapter>
