<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-common SYSTEM "../libs-common/xubuntu-common.ent">
%xubuntu-common;
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-docs SYSTEM "../libs/xubuntu-docs.ent">
%xubuntu-docs;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../libs-common/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
<!ENTITY language "C">
]>
<chapter id="guide-keeping-safe">
	<title>Keeping your computer and personal information safe</title>

	<para>Keeping your computer and personal information safe from security threats is one of the most important aspects of computing today. This guide aims to help you achieving a higher level of security. Pay particular attention to the following subsections:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para><xref linkend="keep-software-uptodate" /></para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><xref linkend="passwords-important" /></para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><xref linkend="script-applications-sources" /></para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><xref linkend="clean-browser" /></para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><xref linkend="email-security" /></para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<section id="keep-software-uptodate">
		<title>Keep your software up to date</title>

		<para>Security updates are very important. They are the best defense you
			have against the people who want to harm your computer, and you should
			install them immediately. When a security update is released, hackers
			already know how to abuse computers that are not up-to-date. In the
			worst case scenario, they are searching for victims to hack with
			automated programs in under a few hours.</para>
		<para>Automatic security updates are enabled by default in Xubuntu. If you
			want to change the settings for the automatic updates, go to the
			<guilabel>Updates</guilabel> tab under &software-properties; and change
			the settings to your liking.</para>
		<warning><para>If you disable automatic updates, you are lowering the
			security level of your computer. When the automatic updates are turned
			off, it's essential to remember to upgrade manually often.</para></warning>
		<tip><para>If you use an Internet connection with limited bandwidth and do
			not want to use automatic updates, remember to update every time you
			have access to an unlimited connection.</para></tip>
	</section>

	<section id="passwords">
		<title>Passwords</title>

		<section id="passwords-important">
			<title>Use strong and unique passwords for important accounts</title>

			<para>Using strong and unique passwords for important and sensitive
				accounts helps prevent unauthorized access to your personal
				information, identity theft and direct financial losses. Consider
				the following scenario:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Alice uses identical passwords for mytrustedbank.com and insecureblog.com</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>insecureblog is hacked and Alice’s information and password are stolen</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Hackers can now access Alice’s bank account and steal her money</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>

			<para>Password reuse can turn into a disaster. You should pay attention
				to use unique and strong passwords for the following services:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para><emphasis>Email accounts</emphasis>. Email accounts can be used to reset all your other passwords via the “Forgotten password” links found on all websites.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><emphasis>Key stores and password managers</emphasis>. It is worth having a good password for those services, since they allow you to avoid typing many other passwords!</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><emphasis>Accounts related to banking</emphasis>, including PayPal and other payment sites. If someone can access these, they can steal your money.</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>

		<section id="passwords-strong">
			<title>What is a strong password?</title>

			<para>The strength of a password depends on how hard it is for an
				attacker to guess it. Attackers use special programs that can make
				millions of guesses per second, so weak passwords don’t stand a
				chance.</para>

			<para>Some passwords (like <literal>monkey</literal>, <literal>password</literal>,
				<literal>test</literal>, <literal>123456</literal>) are extremely
				common. If you use those common passwords, your accounts will be
				hacked easily. However, adding capital letters, numbers or symbols
				is often not enough to turn a weak password into a strong one. This
				is because people reliably pick the same additional symbols and
				numbers (for instance, <literal>monkey1</literal> is more common
				than <literal>mo5nkey</literal>, and also more common than
				<literal>monkey hoover</literal>).</para>

			<para>It is better to choose a longer secret, such as a pass phrase
				(for example <literal>correct horse stable battery</literal>), than
				a secret that is both hard to remember and easy to crack. Consider
				using a series of common words which you can easily remember. Do not
				pick words that people around you would naturally associate with you
				(for instance, you should not pick poker related words if you play
				poker every day).</para>
		</section>

		<section id="passwords-reuse">
			<title>How to reuse passwords safely?</title>

			<para>While using the same password for multiple accounts is not
				encouraged, everybody ends up doing this, even security experts.
				However, many commonly used websites get compromised by hackers
				every year. Some of them might even purposefully sell their users'
				passwords to third-parties. There is no definitive agreement
				among security researchers on how to reduce the risk of reusing
				passwords, but you should consider the following:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Separate your professional password from your personal passwords.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Avoid mixing passwords between websites where attackers can damage your reputation and low-value websites.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Use a password you're willing to lose for sites you do not trust.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Do not "waste" passwords on websites you connect to once a year. Make up a random password and use the "forgotten password" feature next time.</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>

		<section id="passwords-when-change">
			<title>When to change your password?</title>

			<para>You don’t need to change your passwords every other day. In many
				cases, if an attacker could steal your password, they will be able
				to steal it again in the future.</para>
			<para>If you do need to change your password, you must pick one that is
				<emphasis>actually</emphasis> different from the previous one. For
				example, <literal>monkey5</literal> is not an acceptable substitute
				for <literal>monkey4</literal>, and it will be easily guessed by an
				attacker who already stole your previous password!</para>
		</section>

		<section id="passwords-change-login">
			<title>How to change your login password</title>

			<para>To change your password, follow the steps below:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Open &wm-users-groups;</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Click on your username on the list</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Click <guilabel>Change...</guilabel> next to the <guilabel>Password</guilabel> label</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>First enter your <guilabel>Current password</guilabel></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Now you can either</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>Generate a random password by selecting <guilabel>Generate random password</guilabel> and pressing <guibutton>Generate</guibutton></para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>Choose your new password yourself by typing the new password to the <guilabel>New password</guilabel> and <guilabel>Confirmation</guilabel> fields</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>Finally, click <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to confirm the password change</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<caution><para>While it is possible to make Xubuntu log in automatically
				on boot within the user dialog, automatic login is highly discouraged
				because it provides less security for your system. Please turn on
				automatic login on only if you can trust everybody that has access to
				the computer.</para></caution>
		</section>

		<section id="passwords-stolen">
			<title>Watch out for stolen passwords occasionally</title>

			<para>Websites like <ulink url="&haveibeenpwned;">haveibeenpwned.com</ulink>
				can tell you if your email address or username appears amongst
				databases of stolen passwords. It is a good idea to check it every
				other month. Besides, you may occasionally hear about a service you
				use in the news, or get an email from a service provider informing
				you that they have been hacked. When you are confident that a
				password has been compromised, you should:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>identify all the services where you used that password</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>change your password on all those services</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>verify the recent activity on the concerned accounts (watch out for money transfers; also, email services often keep a log of your recent connections with IP addresses and locations)</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<warning><para><emphasis>Never</emphasis> reveal your 
				<emphasis>password</emphasis> to a third-party website. The website
				above is OK to use because asks for an email address, which is
				relatively public information. It does not ask for a password.
				Websites that ask for your password will most likely misuse
				it.</para></warning>
		</section>

		<section id="password-managers">
			<title>What about password managers?</title>

			<para>Password managers are a very convenient way of using many unique
				passwords without having to remember them all!</para>

			<tip><para>There are several password managers available in the
				<application>Ubuntu Software Center</application>, including
				<application>KeePassX</application> and
				<application>PaSaffe</application>.</para></tip>

			<para>Some password managers, like <application>KeePassX</application>
				can synchronise your passwords across devices, including Windows or
				OS X computers. You should be aware of a few limitations, if you
				decide to use a password manager:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Online password managers can be hacked too. Do not store your email or bank passwords in a password manager.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Use a memorable password to unlock your password manager! If you lose that password, you could end up losing access to all your accounts (another good reason not to store emails in your password manager).</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Proprietary password managers should not be trusted. Nobody knows what they do with your passwords.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>You may need to use some accounts from your friends or family’s devices. For those accounts, you can tell your password manager to use a specific and memorable password instead of a random password.</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>If you keep the above advice in mind, password managers can be a
				great way to stay more secure, more easily!</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="good-online-security">
		<title>Tips for good online security</title>

		<section id="script-applications-sources">
			<title>Do not run scripts or install applications from unknown sources</title>
	
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Install applications from the repository whenever possible.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>When running a script found on a troubleshooting or support website or given to you on IRC, take a moment to look at it, or ask a third-party to confirm what the script does. Be especially wary of scripts that require root access, as they could compromise other users' accounts.</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>

		<section id="clean-browser">
			<title>Keep your browser clean for sensitive activities</title>

			<para>Web browser extensions are a popular mechanism among hackers for
				harming users. They are especially relevant to Linux, since they are
				compatible with all platforms. Malicious extensions could steal your
				passwords, monitor your activity online for advertising, abuse your
				social media accounts or steal your money.</para>
			<para>You can take measures to limit the risks you expose yourself to:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Never install an extension that is not distributed by your browser vendor</para></listitem>
				<!-- Mention URL for Firefox? &firefox-addons; -->
				<listitem><para>On Firefox, use a separate user profile for sensitive activities like banking and e-shopping. Firefox user profiles do not share extensions (see <ulink url="&firefox-profiles;">Use the Profile Manager to create and remove Firefox profiles</ulink>).</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>On Chrome and other browsers, use the Incognito mode for sensitive activities like banking and e-shopping. Incognito mode disables extensions.</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>

		<section id="email-security">
			<title>Remember email security</title>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Do not open email attachments from people that you don’t know, or if you think the content of the email is incoherent or suspicious (for example invoices coming from people you have never heard of).</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Do not reply to spam. This will inform spammers that your email address is active, and it will incite them to send you more spam.</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>

		<section id="firewalls">
			<title>Consider firewalls if your computer hosts Internet services</title>

			<para>If you run public facing Internet services, or are not on a NAT,
				you should consider using a firewall. Most home users are not
				concerned by this measure.</para>
			<para>Understand that firewalls are not very useful in their default
				settings. You should consider what you want to achieve and configure
				the firewall accordingly. Firewalls can protect you against
				denial of service attacks, limit access to a service to specific IP
				addresses or inspect and reject suspicious packets. However, they
				cannot protect you against unknown or emerging threats, and they do
				not replace the need to install security updates.</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="backup-regularly">
		<title>Back up on a regular basis</title>

		<para>A problem that you may occasionally encounter is the unexpected loss
			of some of your work and settings for one reason or another. The causes
			of such data loss are many and varied; they could be anything from a
			power failure to accidentally deleting a file. It is highly recommended
			that you make regular backup copies of your important files so that, if
			you do encounter a problem, you will not have lost those files.</para>
		<para>It is wise to store backup copies of files separately from your
			computer; that is, you should make use of some form of file storage
			which is not permanently attached to your computer. Options include but
			are not limited to writable CDs and DVDs, external hard disks, USB
			disks and other computers on the network.</para>
		<para>A simple way of backing up your files is to manually copy them to a
			safe location (see above) by using the <application>File Browser</application>
			as well as the <application>Archive Manager</application> which lets
			you compress files and pack them together. Alternatively, you
			can use a dedicated backup application.</para>
		<para>General advice on how to keep good backups:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Back up on a regular basis</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Always test your backups after you make them to ensure
				that they have been made correctly</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Label your backups clearly and keep them in a safe
				place</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<tip><para>There are numerous dedicated backup applications available
			in the <application>Ubuntu Software Center</application>, including
			<application>Dejà Dup</application> and
			<application>luckyBackup</application>.</para></tip>
		<tip><para>If you use online backup services like Dropbox, it is a good
			idea to first encrypt your documents and upload an encrypted archive.
			This will prevent the online services staff from accessing your
			documents.</para></tip>
		<tip><para>Backups can also be an effective protection against
			ransomware, which encrypts your data and will only decrypt it if you
			pay the developers. To keep clean from ransomware, avoid installing
			applications from unknown sources. For more information, see
			<xref linkend="script-applications-sources" />.</para></tip>
	</section>

	<section id="safety-encryption">
		<title>Consider encryption</title>

		<para>Full disk encryption is a good measure to protect your computers
			content should it get stolen. You should consider it if, for instance,
			your job involves valuable Intellectual Property or executive
			responsibilities. Remember that full disk encryption will not protect
			you if you do not shutdown your computer when you are not using it.</para>
		<tip><para>The easiest way to enable full disk encryption is to do it
			during the installation.</para></tip>
		<tip><para>You can also create encrypted volumes using dedicated software,
			for example LUKS. Encrypted volumes can contain arbitrary data of any
			length. You can mount them like you would insert a USB key when you
			need to access their content, and keep them closed the rest of the
			time. Describing the process to do this is outside the scope of this
			documentation, but there are numerous tutorials online.</para></tip>
			<!-- Preferred link? -->
	</section>

	<section id="shared-environment">
		<title>Using your computer in a shared environment</title>

		<section id="no-shared-accounts">
			<title>Do not use shared accounts</title>

			<para>When Xubuntu is installed, it is set up for a single person to use.
				If more than one person will use the computer, it is best for each
				person to have their own user account. To read more about adding users,
				refer to <xref linkend="users-groups" />.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="lock-your-screen">
			<title>Lock your screen while away</title>

			<para>Locking your screen prevents other people from accessing your
				computer while you are away from it. All of your applications and work
				remain open while the screen is locked.</para>
			<para>To lock the screen, press &key;<keycap>Ctrl+Alt+Delete</keycap> or
				click &wm-lock-screen;.</para>
			<para>To unlock the screen, move the mouse or press a key. Then, type your
				password and either press the &key;<keycap>Enter</keycap> key or click
				the <guibutton>Unlock</guibutton> button.</para>
			<para>If more than one person has a user account on your computer and the
				screen is locked, other users can press the triangle button to the
				right of the user name, select their name from the list and enter their
				password to use the computer, even while the screen is locked. They will
				be unable to access your currently open work and you will be able to
				switch back to your locked session when they have finished using the
				computer.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>
