<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-ent SYSTEM "../libs/xubuntu.ent">
%xubuntu-ent;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
<!ENTITY language "C">
]>
<chapter id="guide-desktop">
	<title>Getting to know your desktop environment</title>

	<para>When your computer has finished booting up, and after entering your login data, you will
		arrive at the Xubuntu desktop. It comes with many features that make your life easy and it is
		well worth the time to get to know your way around it.</para>

	<section id="desktop">
		<title>Desktop</title>

		<para>Your desktop has two panels: one on top, which is always visible, and one at the bottom
			of the screen, which is hidden when not in use.</para>

		<section id="desktop-top-panel">
			<title>Top Panel</title>

			<para>The top panel is mainly used for starting applications and navigating to different
				places on your computer. It also comes with an <guilabel>Action button</guilabel>,
				<guilabel>Workspace Switcher</guilabel>, <guilabel>Notification Area</guilabel> and a
				clock. Clicking on &appmenu; will open the <guilabel>Applications Menu</guilabel>,
				offering you many choices of applications to start. Note that you can also access your
				<guilabel>Settings</guilabel>, <guilabel>Help</guilabel>, and a logout dialog from the	
				menu. Clicking on the <guilabel>Action button</guilabel> (your username in the upper
				right) will bring up a menu with choices for logging out, shutting down, locking the
				screen, switching users and, depending on your hardware, suspending or hibernating your
				computer.</para>

			<para>To the left of the <guilabel>Action button</guilabel> is the <guilabel>Workspace
				Switcher</guilabel> which looks like two colored rectangles. Clicking on these allows
				you to instantly switch between two different workspaces which can each contain
				different running applications. If you're used to running many applications
				simultaneously, this is a handy way to keep your screen from getting too crowded.</para>

			<para>To the left of the clock is the <guilabel>Notification Area</guilabel>. Here you will
				see icons displaying the status of your network connection, mail and messaging notices
				and the system sound volume. Other notification icons may appear as necessary, for
				instance when software updates are available.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="desktop-bottom-panel">
			<title>Bottom Panel</title>

			<para>At the bottom of the screen is a hidden panel called the Launcher Panel. To see this
				panel, drag your mouse to the bottom of the screen and pause there. As the name
				indicates, the purpose of this panel is to provide you with a quick way to launch any of
				the most commonly used Xubuntu applications with a single click. Hovering over each icon
				with your mouse will display the name of the application.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="desktop-desktop">
			<title>The Desktop</title>

			<para>The default desktop has just three icons on it: <guilabel>Home</guilabel>,
				<guilabel>File System</guilabel> and <guilabel>Trash</guilabel> (icons for removable
				devices, like CDs or flash drives, will also appear if any of those devices are
				present). You can customize your desktop by right-clicking in a blank area and choosing
				<menuchoice><guimenuitem>Desktop Settings</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. From here you can
				change the wallpaper and modify menu and icon behavior.</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="files-directories">
		<title>Files and directories</title>

		<para>Xubuntu comes with Xfce's file manager called <application>Thunar</application>. For
			simplicity's sake, we will just refer to it as the File Manager. Load it from
			&file-manager; or by double-clicking the <guilabel>Home</guilabel> or <guilabel>File
			System</guilabel> icons on your desktop.</para>

		<section id="files-directories-navigation">
			<title>Navigation</title>

			<para>The File Manager's default view consists of a shortcut pane on the left side, the
				main area on the right, and a pathbar above the main area. The shortcut pane provides
				shortcuts to different folders on your system. The first shortcut will lead to your home
				directory, the directory where you store all your personal data, and will therefore have
				the name of the current user. That directory will probably appear empty. The
				<guilabel>File System</guilabel> shortcut will take you to the root of your filesystem.
				You may want to explore it a bit, even though it will be confusing to you if you are new
				to Linux. Just click on the different folders and see what's inside. When you're done,
				return to your home directory by clicking on the top shortcut.</para>

			<tip><para>You can add your own shortcuts by simply dragging folders to the shortcut pane.
				This will allow you to access important folders instantly!</para></tip>

			<para>The main area will always display the contents of the current folder. Double-click on
				folders to enter them, and right-click on files/folders to get a pop-up window offering
				you some choices of what to do with them. Select multiple files by dragging a rectangle
				over them with the mouse. Alternatively, select one file, hold down the <keycap>Shift</keycap>
				key, and increase/decrease the selection using the arrow keys.</para>

			<para>The pathbar will always show you the path you took to get to the current directory.
				You can click on any pathbar icon to change to the directory it represents. Note that
				right-clicking on pathbar icons will also bring up a pop-up window with some options.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="files-directories-creating-deleting">
			<title>Creating and deleting files and folders</title>

			<para>To create a new document, right-click on some empty space in your home directory and
			select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Create Document</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Empty
			File</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the pop-up menu. The File Manager will prompt you for
			a name. Just go with the suggested name for now. After this, you will see the new file in
			your home directory. Right-click on it and choose
			<menuchoice><guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. This will show you some
			details about the file. Right-click on the file once more and choose
			<menuchoice><guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to remove it. The file will be
			put into the Trash.</para>

			<tip><para>If you ever want to undo the deleting of a file, open <guilabel>Trash</guilabel>,
				right-click the file and click
				<menuchoice><guimenuitem>Restore</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></tip>

			<para>To create a new folder, right-click on the empty space, and choose
				<menuchoice><guimenuitem>Create Folder</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. You will be prompted
				for a name. Type something and hit <keycap>&key;Enter</keycap>. You will see this new folder
					in your home directory. Double-click on it to enter it. To rename or remove the
					folder, right-click on it and choose the appropriate option from the pop-up menu.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="files-directories-copying">
			<title>Copying</title>

			<para>To copy and move files on your computer, just click and drag files and folders to
				other folders.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="files-directories-removable-devices">
			<title>Removable devices</title>

			<para>When inserting CDs, USB sticks or other removable media into your computer, or
				hooking up removable devices like a music player, Xubuntu should automatically detect
				the new device. For example, after inserting a CD into your optical drive, you will see
				a new shortcut in the left pane of the <application>File Manager</application>
				representing the CD. Clicking on it will open the CD in the main area, just like
				clicking on a regular folder. To remove the CD, right-click on the shortcut, and choose
				<menuchoice><guimenuitem>Eject Volume</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The same applies for
				any other removable media.</para>

			<note><para>Please note that pressing the eject button on your CD drive may not work. This
				may be surprising to some users, but it is in fact the expected behavior. Before the CD
				can be ejected, it needs to be properly "released" (unmounted) by the system. To remove
				a CD, always right-click on its shortcut and choose
				<menuchoice><guimenuitem>Eject Volume</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></note>
		</section>

		<section id="files-directories-customizing-thunar">
			<title>Customizing Thunar</title>

			<para>There are many ways to customize the <application>File Manager</application>. If you do
				not like the way the icons are displayed, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>View</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>View as	Detailed List</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to have the contents of
				the current directory displayed as a list.</para>

			<para>You can have the <application>File Manager</application> display a location bar
				instead of the pathbar by selecting <menuchoice><guimenu>View</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Location Selector</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Toolbar
				Style</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. If you prefer a tree view in the left pane, choose
				<menuchoice><guimenu>View</guimenu><guimenuitem>Side Pane</guimenuitem>
				<guimenuitem>Tree</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="customizing-appearance">
		<title>Customizing the appearance</title>

		<para>If you want to customize the appearance of your Xubuntu system, the options are
			unlimited. Here's a few good starting points.</para>

		<section id="customizing-wallpaper">
			<title>Changing your wallpaper</title>

			<para>To change your wallpaper to any of the other default wallpapers:</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Right-click the desktop</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>From the context menu, select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Desktop
					Settings</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>In the <guilabel>Background</guilabel> tab, select a new wallpaper
					image</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>If you have multiple monitors, you will have another set of tabs under
					<guilabel>Background</guilabel>; use these to specify which monitors wallpaper you
					want to change.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>If you have multiple monitors, you can set the wallpaper on the primary
					monitor to stretch across all monitors.</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<tip><para>If you want to add one or more of your images in this list for future use, you
				can copy or symlink them to &location_backdrops; (needs administrative privileges)</para></tip>

			<para>If you want to set any of your own images as the wallpaper, the easiest way to
				achieve this is:</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Open Thunar and navigate to the directory with the image</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Right-click the image and select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Set as
					wallpaper</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the context menu</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<caution><para>With multiple monitors, this setting will only change the primary monitors
				wallpaper. To change the wallpaper for other monitors, you will need to use the
				dialog described above.</para></caution>
		</section>

		<section id="customizing-panel">
			<title>Customizing your panel configuration</title>

			<para>If you don't like the default panel configuration, including the positioning or the
				applets installed by default, follow the steps below to customize the panel
				configuration:</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Right-click any panel</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>From the context menu, select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Panel</guimenuitem>
					<guimenuitem>Panel Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>On the top of the dialog, you can select which panel you are editing as
					well as add or delete panels</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>In the <guilabel>Display</guilabel> tab, you can control the selected
					panel appearance</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>In the <guilabel>Items</guilabel> tab, you can control the selected
					panel applets and other items</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>

		<section id="customizing-themes">
			<title>Changing your desktop themes</title>

			<para>There are three types of desktop themes:</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>xfwm themes - control how your window borders look. To change your xfwm
					theme, go to &settings-window-manager;. In the <guilabel>Style</guilabel> tab, select
					a new theme to change the window borders appearance.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>GTK themes - control how the content of the windows look. To change your
					GTK theme, go to &settings-appearance;. In the <guilabel>Style</guilabel> tab, select
					a new theme to change the window content appearance.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Icon themes - control how your icons look. To change your icon theme, go
					to &settings-appearance;. In the <guilabel>Icons</guilabel> tab, select a new theme
					to change the icon appearance. Note that not all icon sets will work well with dark
					panel/window backgrounds!</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>If the default selection of themes doesn't satisfy you, you can download and install
				new themes. Some new themes can be installed from the Ubuntu repositories, and more can
				be found on the Internet, for example on <ulink url="&xfce-look;">Xfce-look.org</ulink>.</para>

			<para>If you install new themes from the repositories, they should appear automatically in
				the <application>Settings Manager</application>. If you download a theme from any other
				site, you need to install the theme before it will appear in the <application>Settings
				Manager</application>. To do this, extract the theme package and copy them to:</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>xfwm and GTK themes:</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>&location_themes_user; (this user only)</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>&location_themes_global; (all users)</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>Icon themes:</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>&location_icons_user; (this user only)</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>&location_icons_global; (all users)</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</listitem>

			</itemizedlist>

			<note><para>If these directories do not exist, you should create them first. Copying themes
				for all users will need administrative privileges.</para></note>
		</section>

		<section id="customizing-desktop-effects">
			<title>Disabling and modifying the desktop effects</title>

			<para>While Xubuntu doesn't come with many desktop effects, the Xfce compositor is enabled	
				by default. In the default Xubuntu configuration, the Xfce compositor is used to draw
				shadows for windows and to enable translucent panels. If you have a low-end GPU or you
				don't like the desktop effects mentioned, you can turn off compositor or change the
				settings by navigating to &settings-window-manager-tweaks; and in the
				<guilabel>Compositor</guilabel> tab either unticking <guilabel>Enable display
				compositing</guilabel> or modifying settings.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>
