<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-ent SYSTEM "../libs/xubuntu.ent">
%xubuntu-ent;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
<!ENTITY language "C">
]>
<chapter id="guide-keeping-safe">
	<title>Keeping your computer safe</title>

	<para>This is a brief guide on keeping your computer safe from security
		threats. We will guide you through seven different tips:</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>Change your password regularly</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Don't use shared user accounts</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Keep your software up-to-date</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Lock your screen while away</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Set up a firewall</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Use common sense when working in the web</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Back up on a regular basis</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<section id="change-password">
		<title>Change your password regularly</title>

		<para>In addition to having strong passwords, it is wise to change your
			password regularly. To change your password, follow the steps below:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Open &wm-users-groups;</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Click on your username on the list</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Click <guilabel>Change...</guilabel> next to the <guilabel>Password</guilabel> label</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>First enter your <guilabel>Current password</guilabel></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Now you can either</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>Generate a random password by selecting <guilabel>Generate random password</guilabel> and pressing <guibutton>Generate</guibutton></para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Choose your new password yourself by typing the new password to the <guilabel>New password</guilabel> and <guilabel>Confirmation</guilabel> fields</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
			<listitem><para>Finally, click <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to confirm the password change</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<caution><para>While it is possible to make Xubuntu log in automatically
			on boot within the user dialog, automatic login is highly discouraged
			because it provides less security for your system. Please turn on
			automatic login on only if you can trust everybody that has access to
			the computer.</para></caution>
	</section>

	<section id="no-shared-accounts">
		<title>Don't use shared accounts</title>

		<para>When Xubuntu is installed, it is set up for a single person to use.
			If more than one person will use the computer, it is best for each
			person to have their own user account. To read more about adding users,
			refer to <xref linkend="users-groups" />.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="lock-your-screen">
		<title>Lock your screen while away</title>

		<para>Locking your screen prevents other people from accessing your
			computer while you are away from it. All of your applications and work
			remain open while the screen is locked.</para>
		<para>To lock the screen, press &key;<keycap>Ctrl+Alt+Delete</keycap> or click &wm-lock-screen;.</para>
		<para>To unlock the screen, move the mouse or press a key. Then, type your
			password and either press the &key;<keycap>Enter</keycap> key or click the <guibutton>Unlock</guibutton>
			button.</para>
		<para>If more than one person has a user account on your computer and the
			screen is locked, other users can press the triangle button to the right of the user name and enter their password to use the
			computer, even while the screen is locked. They will be unable to
			access your currently open work and you will be able to switch back to
			your locked session when they have finished using the computer.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="set-up-firewall">
		<title>Set up a firewall</title>

		<para>Firewalls help to prevent security breaches by blocking connections
			to your computer from unknown sources. No firewall is enabled in the
			default Xubuntu installation. However, you have a couple of options for
			enabling a firewall to protect your computer against unauthorized
			access by people on the Internet or your network.</para>
		<para>You can install a firewall from <application>Ubuntu Software Center</application>.
			One such option is <application>Firestarter</application>, which is
			available from	the Universe repository. For help and advice on
			configuring Firestarter, see the
			<ulink url="http://www.fs-security.com/docs.php">Firestarter Online Manual</ulink>.</para>
		<para>More advanced users may wish to use the <application>UFW</application>
			firewall, which is installed, but not enabled, in the default Xubuntu
			installation. See the <ulink url="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/UFW">UFW
			Community Help Wiki</ulink> on the Ubuntu wiki for more information.</para>
		<tip><para>To check that your firewall is working correctly, make use of
			an online firewall testing service such as
			<ulink url="https://www.grc.com/x/ne.dll?bh0bkyd2">ShieldsUP</ulink>.</para></tip>
	</section>

	<section id="use-common-sense-web">
		<title>Use common sense when working in the web</title>
		<para>Here are a few tips for keeping safe online:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Never reply to unsolicited mail (see more info below)
				or even click on the links in an email. Doing so usually results in
				more junk mail being sent to you.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Never click on links in emails which lead to websites
				asking for your password or other confidential information. It is
				possible for the text of the link to give one address when really it
				opens up another (possibly dangerous) address. Instead, type the
				link directly into your web browser yourself and proceed from
				there.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>If a website asks for your financial details, ensure
				that it is secure. In the <application>Firefox</application> web
				browser, secure websites have a padlock icon to the left of the
				address. Click on the padlock to read more information about the
				security of the website. </para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Only download and run software from sources that you
				trust. By default, you can only download software directly from
				Xubuntu.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>Unwanted (unsolicited) mail tends to fall in to one of several
			categories:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Spam (junk) email, where people offer unwanted services
				and products</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Scam emails, where people pretend to ask for help in
				exchange for large sums of money</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Phishing emails, where the message appears to be from a
				bank or other online service, asking you to enter your personal and
				financial details or passwords</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>

	<section id="backup-regularly">
		<title>Back up on a regular basis</title>

		<para>A problem that you may occasionally encounter is the unexpected loss
			of some of your work and settings for one reason or another. The causes
			of such data loss are many and varied; they could be anything from a
			power failure to accidentally deleting a file. It is highly recommended
			that you make regular backup copies of your important files so that, if
			you do encounter a problem, you will not have lost those files.</para>
		<para>It is wise to store backup copies of files separately from your
			computer; that is, you should make use of some form of file storage
			which is not permanently attached to your computer. Options include but
			are not limited to writable CDs and DVDs, external hard disks, USB
			disks and other computers on the network.</para>
		<para>A simple way of backing up your files is to manually copy them to a
			safe location (see above) by using the File Browser as well as the <application>Archive Manager</application> which lets you compress files and pack them together.  Alternatively, you
			can use a dedicated backup application.</para>
		<tip><para>There are numerous dedicated backup applications available
			in the <application>Ubuntu Software Center</application>, including
			<application>Dejà Dup</application> and
			<application>luckyBackup</application>.</para></tip>
		<para>General advice on how to keep good backups:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Back up on a regular basis</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Always test your backups after you make them to ensure
				that they have been made correctly</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Label your backups clearly and keep them in a safe
				place</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>

</chapter>
