<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-ent SYSTEM "../libs/xubuntu.ent">
%xubuntu-ent;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
<!ENTITY language "C">
]>
<chapter id="internet-networks">
	<title>Connecting to Internet and Networks</title>

	<para>Xubuntu uses <application>NetworkManager</application> to manage wired, wireless, mobile broadband, VPN and DSL connections. <application>NetworkManager</application> also keeps passwords secure by utilizing the user's keyring to store passphrases.</para>

	<para><application>NetworkManager</application> is the little icon in the upper panel in the top right of your screen. When not connected, the icon shows two grayed out arrows pointing up and down. When you are connected, the icon is different depending on the network type in use.</para>

	<section id="network-connections">
		<title>Network connections</title>

		<section id="network-connect-disconnect">
			<title>Connecting and disconnecting</title>

			<para><application>NetworkManager</application> will automatically use a wired network, if one is available.</para>

			<para>To see all available connections, click the NetworkManager icon. To connect to a network, click the network name.</para>

			<note><para>If you are connecting to a wireless network for the first time, security details may be needed. If so, a dialog box will open. In most cases, the security type will be detected automatically. If not, select the security type from the <guilabel>Wi-Fi Security</guilabel> drop-down box, enter the authentication details and press <guibutton>Connect</guibutton>.</para></note>

			<para>To disconnect from a network, click the NetworkManager icon, and select Disconnect under the appropriate connection type. To disable (and re-enable) wired and/or wireless connections all together, click the NetworkManager icon and select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Enable Networking</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Enable Wi-Fi</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. These choices are toggles. Their enabled/disabled status is indicated by the presence/absence of a check mark.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="network-configure">
			<title>Configuring connections</title>

			<para>If you need to configure your connections, click the NetworkManager icon and select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. In the dialog, you will see expandable rows for each connection type. Select the appropriate network and press <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> or press <guibutton>Add</guibutton> to set up new networks.</para>

			<note><para>To be able to connect to certain networks you might need connection details which you will get from your network administrator or your Internet Service Provider.</para></note>
		</section>

		<section id="network-information">
			<title>Connection information</title>

			<para>To see the connection information, click the NetworkManager icon and select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Information</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Your active network connections will be displayed in the <guilabel>Active Connections</guilabel> dialog, each in a separate tab.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="network-sharing">
			<title>Sharing your connection to another computer</title>

			<para>You can share your connection to another computer using an Ethernet cable. This can be carried out by clicking the NetworkManager icon, selecting <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, and then adding a new wireless connection (or editing the existing one). In the connection properties window, select <guilabel>IPv4 Settings</guilabel>, and change <guilabel>Method</guilabel> to <guilabel>Shared to other computers</guilabel> from the drop-down list.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="network-modems">
			<title>Dialup modems</title>

			<para>Unfortunately, dialup modems are not supported by <application>NetworkManager</application>. To read about connecting with a dialup modem, please refer to the <ulink url="&communitywiki-dialup;">Dialup modem How-to</ulink> on the Ubuntu community wiki.</para>		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="network-troubleshooting">
		<title>Network troubleshooting</title>

		<para>Before attempting any troubleshooting, ensure that the network connections are enabled:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Click the NetworkManager icon in the notification area</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Check <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Enable Networking</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Check <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Enable Wi-Fi</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>If your network connection still doesn't work:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>For wired (Ethernet) connections, please see <xref linkend="network-troubleshooting-general" /></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>For wireless connections, please see both <xref linkend="network-troubleshooting-general" /> and <xref linkend="network-troubleshooting-wireless" /></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>If your network connection problems are still not resolved, see <xref linkend="network-troubleshooting-advanced" /></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<section id="network-troubleshooting-general">
			<title>General troubleshooting</title>

			<para>If your network connection is not working properly, there are a few tools that can be used to help diagnose the problem.</para>

			<section id="network-troubleshooting-information">
				<title>Get information about the current connection</title>

				<para>To get information about your network connection and network devices, you have two options:</para>

				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>Using <application>NetworkManager</application></para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para>Click on the NetworkManager icon</para></listitem>	
							<listitem><para>Select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Information</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. If <guilabel>Information</guilabel> is disabled, it is likely there is no active connection. Try using <application>ifconfig</application> to find out more.</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>Each active connection will have its own tab where you can find relevant connection information</para></listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>	
						<para>Using <application>ifconfig</application></para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para>Open a terminal (&terminal;) and type the command <userinput>ifconfig</userinput> and press <keycap>&key;Enter</keycap></para></listitem>
							<listitem><para><application>ifconfig</application> will show you extensive information about your connection, including logical or connection name(s) (e.g. eth1) in the left column, IP address in the <guilabel>inet addr</guilabel> column and the MAC address for your device in the <guilabel>HWaddr</guilabel> column</para></listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</section>

			<section id="network-troubleshooting-working">
				<title>Check if a connection is working properly</title>

				<para>A reliable method to check if a connection is working properly is to ping another computer on the network or the Internet.</para>

				<para>To check if your computer is connected to the Internet, open a terminal (&terminal;) and type the command <userinput>ping -c 3 www.xubuntu.org</userinput> and press <keycap>&key;Enter</keycap></para>

				<para>The computer will then attempt to contact www.xubuntu.org three times and display the results. The ping statistics display the number of packets transmitted, how many packets were received, the percentage of packet loss, and the total time spent.</para>

				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>0% packet loss indicates that your computer is connected to the Internet</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Greater than 0% but less than 100% packet loss indicates that your computer has a poor connection to the Internet or a poor wireless signal</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>100% packet loss indicates that your computer has a very bad connection, or is connected to an access point or router that is not connected to the Internet</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>

				<para>If you get an error message that says "www.xubuntu.org can not be found" or "unknown host", then your computer is probably not connected to the Internet or is unable to reach a Domain Name System (DNS) server.</para>
			</section>
		</section>

		<section id="network-troubleshooting-wireless">
			<title>Wireless troubleshooting</title>

			<para>This section covers some common problems faced with wireless support. There is much more information available in the <ulink url="&communitywiki-wifi;">Community Documentation</ulink>.</para>

			<note><para>Please note that the steps in this troubleshooting guide are designed to be carried out in the order shown, unless you are pointed to a different subsection</para></note>

			<section id="network-troubleshoothing-wifi-on">
				<title>Check that the device is turned on</title>

				<para>Many wireless network devices can be turned on or off. Check for a hardware switch or a keyboard function key to turn the wireless device on.</para>

				<para>If the device is turned on, continue to the next topic.</para>
			</section>

			<section id="network-troubleshooting-device-recognized">
				<title>Check if the device is recognized</title>

				<para>Open a terminal (&terminal;) and type the command <userinput>sudo lshw -C network</userinput> and press <keycap>&key;Enter</keycap>. You will see some output, along with the words <guilabel>CLAIMED</guilabel>, <guilabel>UNCLAIMED</guilabel>, <guilabel>ENABLED</guilabel> or <guilabel>DISABLED</guilabel>.</para>

				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para><guilabel>CLAIMED</guilabel> indicates that a driver is loaded but not functioning. Continue to <xref linkend="network-troubleshooting-ndiswrapper" />.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><guilabel>UNCLAIMED</guilabel> indicates that there is no driver loaded. Continue to <xref linkend="network-troubleshooting-ndiswrapper" />.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><guilabel>ENABLED</guilabel> indicates that the driver is installed and working. Continue to section <xref linkend="network-troubleshooting-router" />.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><guilabel>DISABLED</guilabel> indicates the the driver is installed, but disabled. Continue to <xref linkend="network-troubleshoothing-wifi-on" />.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</section>

			<section id="network-troubleshooting-ndiswrapper">
				<title>Using Windows wireless drivers</title>

				<para>Xubuntu supports a system known as <application>NDISWrapper</application>. This allows you to use a Windows wireless device driver under Xubuntu. To start using <application>NDISWrapper</application>:</para>

				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>Obtain the Windows driver for your network device and locate the file that ends with .inf</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Install the <literal>&package;ndisgtk</literal> package</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Go to &ndisgtk;</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Select <guibutton>Install new driver</guibutton></para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Choose the location of your Windows .inf file and click <guibutton>Install</guibutton></para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton></para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</section>

			<section id="network-troubleshooting-router">
				<title>Checking for a connection to the router</title>

				<para>Open a terminal (&terminal;) and type the command <userinput>iwconfig</userinput> and press <keycap>&key;Enter</keycap>.</para>

				<para>If the <guilabel>ESSID</guilabel> for your router is displayed, there may be a problem with ACPI support. Boot Xubuntu with the <literal>pci=noacpi</literal> option.</para>
			</section>
		</section>

		<section id="network-troubleshooting-advanced">
			<title>Advanced troubleshooting</title>

			<para>The following troubleshooting methods are a bit more technical. Please try these methods only if the above methods failed.</para>

			<section id="network-troubleshooting-ip-assignment">
				<title>Checking IP assignment</title>

				<para>Open a terminal (&terminal;) and type the command <userinput>ifconfig</userinput> and press <keycap>&key;Enter</keycap>. If there is an IP address displayed, continue to <xref linkend="network-troubleshooting-dns" />.</para>

				<para>From the terminal enter the following command, replacing <literal>eth1</literal> with the name of the connection shown in the output from the <application>ifconfig</application> command: <userinput>sudo dhclient eth1</userinput></para>

				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>If you receive a message that says bound to <literal>xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx</literal> continue to <xref linkend="network-troubleshooting-dns" /></para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>If not, reboot the system</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</section>

			<section id="network-troubleshooting-dns">
				<title>Check Domain Name Servers (DNS)</title>

				<para>Open a terminal (&terminal;) and type the command <userinput>nm-tool</userinput> and press <keycap>&key;Enter</keycap>.</para>

				<para>To check if the listed DNS works, open a terminal (&terminal;) and type the command <userinput>dig xubuntu.org</userinput> and press <keycap>&key;Enter</keycap>.  If you see the word <literal>NOERROR</literal>in the header section of the output, your DNS is working.</para>

				<para>If there are no DNS settings listed, contact your Internet Service Provider (ISP), and find out your primary and secondary domain name servers. Once you have this information, continue to <xref linkend="network-connect-disconnect" /> and <xref linkend="network-configure" /> if needed.</para>
			</section>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="connecting-servers">
		<title>Connecting to servers</title>

		<para>To connect to various types of servers, you can use &gigolo;. To connect to a server, follow the steps below:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Go to <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Connect</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Select the appropriate <guilabel>Service type</guilabel> and insert connection information</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Click <guibutton>Connect</guibutton>; if you are attempting to connect to a server that requires you to log in, you will be prompted to enter a password</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>Upon successfully connecting to the server, an icon labeled with connection details will appear in the <application>Gigolo</application> window. To bookmark connections, right-click on a connection and select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Create Bookmark</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. In the <guilabel>Edit Bookmarks</guilabel> dialog, you can name the bookmark and set other options, including the option to auto-connect. Once you are done, click <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to create the bookmark.</para>

		<tip><para>The Windows Share username should be in the format DOMAIN\username</para></tip>

		<note><para>For SAMBA Networks (Windows shares), the package <literal>&package;gvfs-backends</literal> needs to be installed in order to connect using the <application>Thunar File Manager</application>.</para></note>
	</section>
</chapter>
