<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-ent SYSTEM "../libs/xubuntu.ent">
%xubuntu-ent;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
<!ENTITY language "C">
]>
<chapter id="media-apps">
	<title>Media applications</title>

	<section id="media-music">
		<title>Music</title>

		<section id="media-music-listen">
			<title>Listening to music</title>

			<para>You can use <application>gmusicbrowser</application> and <application>Parole Media Player</application> to listen to music on your computer. <application>Parole Media Player</application> may open audio files when they are double-clicked, but <application>gmusicbrowser</application> is better at handling large music collections. Initially, <application>gmusicbrowser</application> will not automatically search for music files on your computer and you will have to manually direct <application>gmusicbrowser</application> to your music files by doing the following:</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Open &gmusicbrowser;</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Open the menu (a gear at the top right) and click <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Settings</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>In the <guilabel>Settings</guilabel> dialog, go to the <guilabel>Library</guilabel> tab</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Click <guibutton>Add Folder</guibutton> and choose the directory that contains your music files and press <guibutton>OK</guibutton>; your selection will now appear in the <guilabel>Settings</guilabel> dialog</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>If you wish to add other locations of music files repeat the previous step, or otherwise, press <guibutton>Close</guibutton></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><application>gmusicbrowser</application> will begin to scan your library. After the <guilabel>Scanning</guilabel> progress bar disappears, you may have to change views (to the left of the search) or restart <application>gmusicbrowser</application> to see your library.</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>

		<section id="media-music-wrong-data">
			<title>I see wrong metadata (song names, covers) for my tracks in gmusicbrowser</title>

			<para>Some music player applications fetch cover art and other information about songs from the internet. However, <application>gmusicbrowser</application> only searches for cover art when you request. Simply right-click the album artwork, and select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Search Picture</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. You can change the search query or service, but the defaults often work well. Select an image and save it to the album directory.</para>

			<para>Sometimes, your music player may not be able to identify a particular song or album correctly. If this is the case, you can add the correct information manually by right-clicking the music file displayed in <application>gmusicbrowser</application>, selecting <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Song Properties</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and entering the appropriate information in the corresponding fields.</para>

			<para>If you prefer to search for the image yourself, find an album cover on the internet (or other sources) and save the image as <filename>cover.jpg</filename> in the album directory. Additionally, you can drag the cover art onto the cover art placeholder in <application>gmusicbrowser</application> or right-click and select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Set Picture</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="media-portable">
			<title>Portable music players</title>

			<para>Xubuntu will work with most portable audio players, including iPods. Normally, all you have to do is plug the player into your computer and then use <application>File Manager</application> to manually copy songs to and from the player.</para>

			<note><para>Newer iPods (6th generation and newer) will not work automatically with Xubuntu unless you have done an initial synchronization with <application>iTunes</application> first.</para></note>

			<para>If you have a portable music player which can also display photos and videos, you may prefer to use <application>Banshee</application>, which is a music player with good support for such devices. iPod owners may also like to try specialized applications such as <application>GPixPod</application> and <application>gtkpod</application> for handling multimedia.</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="media-movie-dvd-video">
		<title>Movies, DVDs and videos</title>

		<para>You can watch movies and video clips with the <application>Parole Media Player</application>.</para>

		<section id="media-play-dvd">
			<title>Playing DVDs</title>

			<para>In order to play DVDs you must install some additional software. Unfortunately, DVD support cannot be provided by default in Xubuntu due to legal restrictions in some countries.</para>

			<caution><para>Read <xref linkend="software-repositories-restricted" /> before following the instructions below. There are some legal issues that you should be aware of.</para></caution>

			<para>To be able to play DVDs, do the following:</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Install the <literal>&package;libdvdnav4</literal>, <literal>&package;libdvdread4</literal> and <literal>&package;gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly</literal> packages.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>If you would like to play encrypted DVDs, open &terminal; and type the following into the <application>Terminal</application> followed by the <keycap>&key;Enter</keycap> key: <userinput>sudo /usr/share/doc/libdvdread4/install-css.sh</userinput></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Enter your password if prompted. The <literal>&package;libdvdcss2</literal> package will be downloaded and installed from a website.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Insert a DVD into your drive. It should open automatically in the <application>Parole Media Player</application>.</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>

		<section id="media-play-video">
			<title>Playing video</title>

			<para><application>Parole</application> supports most video types. If you try to play an unsupported video file, <application>Parole</application> may notify you of a missing plugin. You can then install this plugin by following the wizard. Afterwards, you may need to restart <application>Parole</application>.</para>

			<para>If you are having difficulties getting a video to stream in your browser <application>Parole</application> supports streaming most types of video. To open a video in <application>Parole</application>, right-click the video and select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Open with Parole Media Player</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>

			<section id="media-video-restricted">
				<title>Restricted formats</title>

				<para>Some video formats, such as Adobe Flash, QuickTime and Windows Media Video, are proprietary and so support for them cannot be included in Xubuntu by default. You must install some extra software to allow playback.</para>

				<para>In order to play the most common proprietary formats in <application>Parole</application> or <application>Firefox</application>, install the <literal>&package;xubuntu-restricted-extras</literal> package (see <xref linkend="software-repositories-restricted" /> for more information).</para>
			</section>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="media-photos-cameras">
		<title>Photos and cameras</title>

		<section id="photos-import">
			<title>Importing photos from a digital camera</title>

			<para>Xubuntu automatically detects most digital cameras when you plug them in, and will offer to import your photos automatically. To import photos from your camera:</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Plug-in and switch on the camera by placing it in review mode. Xubuntu should ask you if you would like to import the photos that the camera contains.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Click on <guibutton>Import</guibutton>. You should then see a preview of the photos.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Choose a location to save your photos to, then click on <guibutton>Import</guibutton>. The photos will be saved to your hard drive.</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>If Xubuntu does not ask you to import the photos, you can do so using <application>gThumb</application>.</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Go to &gthumb;</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guisubmenu>Import From</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Removable Device...</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Select your camera from <guilabel>Source</guilabel></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>You can optionally change <guilabel>Show:</guilabel> to <guilabel>Images</guilabel> to display only your photos</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Select the photos you want by holding <keycap>&key;Ctrl</keycap> and clicking on the desired images or clicking <keycap>&key;Ctrl+A</keycap> to select all photos</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Change the <guilabel>Destination</guilabel>, <guilabel>Event</guilabel>, and <guilabel>Tags</guilabel> fields as you please</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Click <guibutton>Import</guibutton></para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>

		<section id="photos-organize">
			<title>Organizing your photo collection</title>

			<para><application>gThumb</application> provides a complete solution for managing your photo collection. To start it, go to &gthumb;. With <application>gThumb</application>, you can import photos from your digital camera or USB stick, tag them with familiar terms, do touch ups, and edit them in different ways. In addition to this, you can upload photos easily to your Flickr, PicasaWeb album and other online photo galleries. For help with <application>gThumb</application>, check out the help by going to <menuchoice><guimenu>Help</guimenu><guimenuitem>Contents</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="photos-slideshow">
			<title>Watch a slideshow of photos</title>

			<para>If you want to show off your photos in all of their glory, why not run a slideshow of them?</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Open &gthumb;</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Select the directory of photos to view</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>View</guimenu><guimenuitem>Slideshow</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>

		<section id="photos-printing">
			<title>Printing photos</title>

			<para>Printing your photos is great way to share them with others. To print your photos:</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Open the photo you want to print in <application>gThumb</application></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Print</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Select the desired printer</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>You can then adjust various settings like orientation, image quality, etc. by clicking on the appropriate tabs</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>When ready, click the <guibutton>Print</guibutton> button</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>

		<section id="photos-edit">
			<title>Editing and improving photos</title>

			<para>Sometimes, you may need to adjust or touch-up a photo to make it look better or to remove some flaw. <application>gThumb</application> includes a few basic tools for doing this. To access these tools, click the Edit File icon (a palette) on the toolbar and then click on one of the tools at the right of the screen.</para>

			<para>In addition to editing photos, you sometimes want to resize them. To resize photos:</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Open the photo you want to resize in <application>gThumb</application></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>On the toolbar, click <menuchoice><guimenu>Tools</guimenu><guimenuitem>Resize Images</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Adjust the <guilabel>Width</guilabel> or <guilabel>Height</guilabel> as appropriate. The image will be kept to scale. If you want to adjust the width and height independently, uncheck the <guilabel>Preserve original aspect ratios</guilabel> box.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Change the <guilabel>Format</guilabel> if you wish</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Click <guibutton>Execute</guibutton> to resize the photo</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Choose the option for saving the file - you can choose to overwrite or not the old file</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to save the resized photo</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="media-burning">
		<title>Burning CDs and DVDs</title>

		<para>You can make your own CDs and DVDs by burning files onto a blank disc using the CD or DVD writer drive of your computer.</para>

		<para><application>Xfburn</application> is the default application in Xubuntu to complete these tasks. <application>Xfburn</application> allows you to to easily create audio CDs, burn CDs and DVDs with either plain data or disk images and prepare blank re-writable disks for a new burn.</para>

		<para>In order to launch <application>Xfburn</application>, go to &xfburn;.</para>

		<para>Once launched, you can insert a CD-R(W) or DVD-R(W) you wish to write to and then select the button corresponding to the action you wish to take (<guibutton>New Data Composition</guibutton>, <guibutton>Audio CD</guibutton>, etc.).</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
