<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-ent SYSTEM "../libs/xubuntu.ent">
%xubuntu-ent;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
<!ENTITY language "C">
]>
<chapter id="offline-packages">
	<title>Offline Package Management</title>

	<para>The tool <application>apt-offline</application> is available to help keep your computer up to date even if it cannot be kept connected.  There are multiple steps involved in the process of doing this.  With a USB flash drive available to you, this can be managed.</para>

	<section id="offline-repo-update">
		<title>Updating Repositories</title>

		<para>After plugging in a USB flash drive and opening a terminal, you can use apt-offline to generate a request to update what your computer knows about software repositories.  This allows your computer to see if there are bug fixes and/or security updates available to apply to your computer.  This also allows you to know if new software is available.</para>

		<para>From your disconnected computer you enter this at the command line: <userinput>apt-offline set --update apt-offline.sig</userinput></para>

		<para>After that command is done and the <userinput>apt-offline.sig</userinput> is created, copy that to your USB flash drive and take it to another computer.  With apt-offline on that computer, you use that file to download what your disconnected computer needs to update itself.  Assuming you are in the terminal and in the directory on the flash drive containing <userinput>apt-offline.sig</userinput>, you enter <userinput>apt-offline get --bundle bundle.zip apt-offline.sig</userinput>.  Once that command is done, you can remove the USB flash drive and take it back to the disconnected computer.</para>

		<para>Back at the disconnected computer, insert the USB flash drive.  Assuming you have opened a terminal and have navigated to the directory on the flash drive containing the two files you then enter: <userinput>sudo apt-offline install bundle.zip</userinput>.  You will see some program output scroll by and once it completes your repositories will be updated.</para> 
	</section>

	<section id="offline-package-install">
		<title>Installing a Package</title>

		<para>After plugging in a USB flash drive and opening a terminal, you can use apt-offline to grab a package to install.  This action can also be combined with updating your computer's understanding of the contents of the software repositories.  In a disconnected environment, using what connection opportunities you have to the max is key</para>

		<para>In this example, assume you want to install <application>tuxpaint</tuxpaint> and dependencies.  From your disconnected computer you enter this at the command line: <userinput>apt-offline set --install-packages tuxpaint --update apt-offline.sig</userinput></para>

		<para>After that command is done and the <userinput>apt-offline.sig</userinput> is created, copy that to your USB flash drive and take it to another computer.  With apt-offline on that computer, you use that file to download what your disconnected computer needs to update itself.  Assuming you are in the terminal and in the directory on the flash drive containing <userinput>apt-offline.sig</userinput>, you enter <userinput>apt-offline get --bundle bundle.zip apt-offline.sig</userinput>.  The command's output will show an attempt to download updates as to what the repositories look like as well as <application>tuxpaint</application> and the dependencies your system requires.  Once that command is done, you can remove the USB flash drive and take it back to the disconnected computer.</para>

		<para>Back at the disconnected computer, insert the USB flash drive.  Assuming you have opened a terminal and have navigated to the directory on the flash drive containing the two files you then enter: <userinput>sudo apt-offline install bundle.zip</userinput>.  You will see some program output scroll by and once it completes your repositories will be updated.  Once that completes, you can then install <application>tuxpaint</application> by then entering: <userinput>sudo apt-get install tuxpaint</userinput>.</para> 
	</section>

	<section id="other-apt-offline-actions">
		<title>Other Actions</title>

		<para>The graphical tool <application>apt-offline-gui</application> helps you walk through the process for more complicated installations and upgrading applications while following the same basic steps as shown above.  As a mirror to the command-line tool's three modes, you have three buttons to enter specific forms to structure how you wish disconnected application management to proceed much like the steps above.  A key disadvantage, though, to the GUI is that helpful error messages are sometimes not passed along compared to the command line version.</para>

	</section>

</chapter>
