<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-ent SYSTEM "../libs/xubuntu.ent">
%xubuntu-ent;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
<!ENTITY language "C">
]>
<chapter id="settings-preferences">
	<title>Settings and Preferences</title>

	<para>The options to customize Xubuntu to your needs and preferences are virtually unlimited, ranging from desktop looks to low level operation tweaks. The sections in this chapter describe how to keep your personal information updated, customize the looks of the desktop and edit the main applications menu to your liking.</para>
	
	<section id="personal-info">
		<title>Customizing your personal info</title>
		
		<para><application>Mugshot</application> is a lightweight user configuration utility that allows you to easily set the profile image and user details for your user profile and any supported applications.</para>
		
		<para>To launch <application>Mugshot</application> navigate to &mugshot;.</para>
		
		<para>To change your profile image, click the <guibutton>image</guibutton> button on the left of the GUI, select one of the given options and follow the instructions.</para>
		
		<note><para>Mugshot requires the installation of <literal>&package;gstreamer1.0-tools</literal> package to use the <guilabel>Capture from camera...</guilabel> feature.</para></note>
		
		<para>Fill the text-fields with the required personal data and click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton>. When applying these details with <application>Pidgin</application> and/or LibreOffice installed, you will be prompted to update their settings as well.</para>
		
		<warning><para>If the personal data inserted in the <guilabel>First Name</guilabel> and <guilabel>Last Name</guilabel> text-fields differ from the existing values held in <userinput>/etc/passwd</userinput>, you'll be prompted to insert your password as a security measure to prevent unwanted updates to your personal information.</para></warning>
		
		<para>Read more at the <ulink url="&mugshot-help;">Mugshot</ulink> official documentation.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="customizing-appearance">
		<title>Customizing the appearance</title>

		<para>If you want to customize the appearance of your Xubuntu system, the options are
			unlimited. Here are a few good starting points.</para>

		<section id="customizing-wallpaper">
			<title>Changing your wallpaper</title>

			<para>To change your wallpaper to any of the other default wallpapers:</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Right-click the desktop</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>From the context menu, select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Desktop
					Settings</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>In the <guilabel>Background</guilabel> tab, select a new wallpaper
					image</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>If you have multiple monitors, you will have another set of tabs under
					<guilabel>Background</guilabel>; use these to specify which monitor's wallpaper you
					want to change.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>If you have multiple monitors, you can set the wallpaper on the primary
					monitor to stretch across all monitors.</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<tip><para>If you want to add one or more of your images in this list for future use, you
				can copy or symlink them to &location_backdrops; (requires administrative privileges)</para></tip>

			<para>If you want to set any of your own images as the wallpaper, the easiest way to
				achieve this is:</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Open Thunar and navigate to the directory with the image</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Right-click the image and select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Set as
					wallpaper</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the context menu</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<caution><para>With multiple monitors, this setting will only change the primary monitor's
				wallpaper. To change the wallpaper for other monitors, you will need to use the
				dialog described above.</para></caution>
		</section>

		<section id="customizing-panel">
			<title>Customizing your panel configuration</title>

			<para>If you don't like the default panel configuration, including the positioning or the
				applets installed by default, follow the steps below to customize the panel
				configuration:</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Right-click any panel</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>From the context menu, select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Panel</guimenuitem>
					<guimenuitem>Panel Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>At the top of the dialog, you can select which panel to edit, add a new panel
					or delete an existing panel</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>In the <guilabel>Display</guilabel> tab, you can control the selected
					panel appearance</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>In the <guilabel>Items</guilabel> tab, you can control the selected
					panel applets and other items</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>

		<section id="customizing-themes">
			<title>Changing your desktop themes</title>

			<para>There are three types of desktop themes:</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>xfwm themes - control how your window borders look. To change your xfwm
					theme, go to &settings-window-manager;. In the <guilabel>Style</guilabel> tab, select
					a new theme to change the window borders appearance.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>GTK themes - control how the content of the windows look. To change your
					GTK theme, go to &settings-appearance;. In the <guilabel>Style</guilabel> tab, select
					a new theme to change the window content appearance.  The tool <application>gtk-theme-config</application> will also allow you to customize your window look.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Icon themes - control how your icons look. To change your icon theme, go
					to &settings-appearance;. In the <guilabel>Icons</guilabel> tab, select a new theme
					to change the icon appearance. Note that not all icon sets will work well with dark
					panel/window backgrounds!</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>If the default selection of themes doesn't satisfy you, you can download and install
				new themes. Some new themes can be installed from the Ubuntu repositories, and more can
				be found on the Internet, for example on <ulink url="&xfce-look;">Xfce-look.org</ulink>.</para>

			<para>If you install new themes from the repositories, they should appear automatically in
				the <application>Settings Manager</application>. If you download a theme from any other
				site, you need to install the theme before it will appear in the <application>Settings
				Manager</application>. To do this, extract the theme package and copy them to:</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>xfwm and GTK themes:</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>&location_themes_user; (this user only)</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>&location_themes_global; (all users)</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>Icon themes:</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>&location_icons_user; (this user only)</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>&location_icons_global; (all users)</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</listitem>

			</itemizedlist>

			<note><para>If these directories do not exist, you should create them first. Copying themes
				for all users will require administrative privileges.</para></note>
		</section>

		<section id="customizing-desktop-effects">
			<title>Disabling and modifying the desktop effects</title>

			<para>While Xubuntu doesn't come with many desktop effects, the Xfce compositor is enabled	
				by default. In the default Xubuntu configuration, the Xfce compositor is used to draw
				shadows for windows and to enable translucent panels. If you have a low-end GPU or you
				don't like the desktop effects mentioned, you can turn off the compositor or change the
				settings by navigating to &settings-window-manager-tweaks; and in the
				<guilabel>Compositor</guilabel> tab either unticking <guilabel>Enable display
				compositing</guilabel> or modifying settings.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>
