<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-ent SYSTEM "../../libs/xubuntu.ent">
%xubuntu-ent;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
<!ENTITY language "C">
]>
<chapter id="what-is-xubuntu">
	<title>What is Xubuntu?</title>

	<section id="short-introduction">
		<title>A short introduction</title>

		<section id="xubuntu-is">
			<title>Xubuntu is a community-developed, Ubuntu-based Linux operating system.</title>
			<para>Xubuntu is an elegant and easy-to-use operating system. Xubuntu comes with Xfce, which is a stable,
				light and configurable desktop environment.</para>
			<para>Xubuntu is perfect for those who want the most out of their desktops, laptops and netbooks with a modern
				look and enough features for efficient, daily usage. It works well on older hardware too.</para>
			<para>Find out more at the <ulink url="&xubuntu-web;">Xubuntu website</ulink>.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="about-the-name">
			<title>About the name</title>
			<para>The "X" in Xubuntu stands for Xfce, the desktop environment in Xubuntu. While the word "ubuntu" denotes
				the dependency and usage of the Ubuntu core, it also represents the philosophical core of the operating
				system. A rough translation of the word ubuntu is "humanity towards others". To read more about the
				philosophy and ideals behind Ubuntu and Xubuntu, please refer to the <ulink url="&ubuntu-philosophy;">Ubuntu
				Philosophy</ulink> page.</para>
			<para>In addition to using the Ubuntu core, Xubuntu is also using the infrastructure kindly provided and
				sponsored by <ulink url="&canonical-web;">Canonical Ltd.</ulink>, a company founded by Mark	Shuttleworth.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="version-numbering">
			<title>Version numbering</title>
			<para>The Xubuntu version numbering scheme is based on the distribution release date. The first part of the
				release denotes year while the second part denotes the month. For example, the first official Xubuntu
				version was released in June, 2006, thus its version number was 6.06. The latest Long Term Support (LTS)
				version is &last-lts-version;, codenamed &last-lts-codename;.</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="learn-more-about-xubuntu">
		<title>Learn more about what makes Xubuntu</title>

		<section id="about-free-software">
			<title>Free Software</title>
			<para>The Xubuntu project is entirely committed to the principles of free software development; people are
				encouraged to use free software, improve it, and pass it on. You can find out more about free software and
				the ideological and technical philosophy behind it at the <ulink url="&gnu-web;">GNU website</ulink>.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="about-linux">
			<title>Linux</title>
			<para>Linux was brought to life in 1991 by a Finnish student named Linus Torvalds. The Linux kernel is the
				heart of the Xubuntu operating system. A kernel is an important part of any operating system, providing the
				communication bridge between hardware and software. Read more about Linux at the
				<ulink url="&kernel-web;">Linux kernel website</ulink>.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="about-xfce">
			<title>Xfce</title>
			<para>Xfce is a lightweight desktop environment used in Xubuntu. It aims to be fast and low on system
				resources, while still being visually appealing and user friendly. Xfce embodies the traditional UNIX
				philosophy of modularity and re-usability. Read more about Xfce at the <ulink url="&xfce-web;">Xfce
				website</ulink>.</para>
		</section>
	</section>

</chapter>
