<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-common SYSTEM "../../libs-common/xubuntu-common.ent">
%xubuntu-common;
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-user SYSTEM "../libs/xubuntu-user.ent">
%xubuntu-user;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs-common/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
<!ENTITY language "C">
]>
<chapter id="guide-default-apps">
	<title>Quick guide to default applications</title>

	<section id="default-graphics">
		<title>Graphics</title>

		<para><application>Ristretto</application> is an image viewer designed to be very light on resources. More information can be found in the <ulink url="&ristretto-docs;">Ristretto online documentation</ulink>.</para>

		<para><application>Simple Scan</application> is an easy-to-use scan utility designed to do simple tasks like scanning to email or directly to PDF. Read more at the <ulink url="&simple-scan-web;">Simple Scan website</ulink>.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="default-internet">
		<title>Internet</title>

		<para><application>Firefox</application> is a mature and stable web browser which can be extended with a wide variety of available add-ins. Read more on <ulink url="&firefox-help;">Firefox's online help</ulink>.</para>

		<para><application>Thunderbird</application> is a versatile mail client which can handle multiple email accounts and different identities simultaneously. Like Firefox, it can also be enhanced with add-ins to customize its appearance and extend its functionality. If you are migrating from another mail program, <application>Thunderbird</application> allows importing your emails and address books. In <application>Thunderbird</application>, navigate to <menuchoice><guimenu>Tools</guimenu><guimenuitem>Import</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to start the <guilabel>Import assistant</guilabel>. Read more on the <ulink url="&thunderbird-help;">Thunderbird Support page</ulink>.</para>

		<para><application>Pidgin</application> is the default instant messaging client capable of handling MSN, XMPP (Google Talk, Facebook) and more. Read more from <ulink url="&pidgin-help;">Using Pidgin</ulink> at the Pidgin online help.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="default-media">
		<title>Media</title>

		<para><application>gmusicbrowser</application> has been provided as your basic audio player. Read more at <xref linkend="media-music-listen" /> and on the <ulink url="&gmusicbrowser-help;">gmusicbrowser user guide</ulink>.</para>

		<para><application>Parole</application> is a simple media player that can play video and audio files. More information can be found in the <ulink url="&parole-docs;">Parole online documentation</ulink>.</para>

		<note><para>It will be necessary to install <literal>&package;xubuntu-restricted-extras</literal> in order to play proprietary media formats like e.g. MP3.</para></note>

		<para><application>PulseAudio Volume Control</application> is the way to control the different sound sources to their destination. Read more at the <ulink url="&pulseaudio-web;">PulseAudio website</ulink>.</para>

		<para><application>Xfburn</application> is the chosen program for creating your CDs and DVDs.</para>

		<para>To read more about media in Xubuntu, refer to <xref linkend="media-apps" />.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="default-office">
		<title>Office</title>

		<para><application>LibreOffice Writer</application> is a word processor with extensive WYSIWYG word processing capabilities. Read more at the <ulink url="&writer-web;">LibreOffice Writer website</ulink>.</para>

		<para><application>LibreOffice Calc</application> is a spreadsheet editor with a number of unique features, including a system which automatically defines series of graphs, based on information available to the user. Read more at the <ulink url="&calc-web;">LibreOffice Calc website</ulink>.</para>

		<para><application>Dictionary</application> provides an easy way to access a number of different dictionaries across the internet. Read more at the <ulink url="&xfce4-dict-web;">Xfce4 Dictionary online help</ulink>.</para>

		<para><application>Document Viewer</application> is a PDF reader.</para>

		<para><application>Orage</application> has been designed to be a simple but effective calendar application to keep track of your appointments and trigger alarms. Read more at the <ulink url="&orage;">Orage website</ulink>.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="default-system">
		<title>System</title>

		<para><application>Gigolo</application> is an easy way to connect to local and remote file systems. Read more at the <ulink url="&gigolo-web;">Gigolo website</ulink>.</para>

		<para><application>Task Manager</application> provides a graphical overview of running applications. More information can be found in the <ulink url="&xfce4-taskman-web;">Task Manager online documenatation</ulink>.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
