<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-common SYSTEM "../../libs-common/xubuntu-common.ent">
%xubuntu-common;
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-user SYSTEM "../libs/xubuntu-user.ent">
%xubuntu-user;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs-common/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
<!ENTITY language "C">
]>
<chapter id="media-apps">
	<title>Media applications</title>

	<section id="media-music">
		<title>Music</title>

		<section id="media-music-listen">
			<title>Listening to music</title>

			<para>You can use <application>Parole Media Player</application> to listen to music on your computer. <application>Parole Media Player</application> will open audio files when they are double-clicked. Alternatively, you can right click on audio files and select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Open with Parole Media Player</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>

			<para>In order to play some popular audio formats like MP3, you will need to install some additional software. Unfortunately, this software cannot be provided by default in Xubuntu due to legal restrictions in some countries.</para>

			<caution><para>Read <xref linkend="media-video-restricted" /> before following the instructions below. There are some legal issues that you should be aware of.</para></caution>

		</section>

		<section id="media-portable">
			<title>Portable music players</title>

			<para>Xubuntu will work with most portable audio players, including iPods. Normally, all you have to do is plug the player into your computer and then use <application>File Manager</application> to manually copy songs to and from the player.</para>

			<note><para>Newer iPods (6th generation and newer) will not work automatically with Xubuntu unless you have done an initial synchronization with <application>iTunes</application> first.</para></note>

			<para>If you have a portable music player which can also display photos and videos, you may prefer to use <application>Banshee</application>, which is a music player with good support for such devices.  iPod owners may also like to try specialized applications such as <application>GPixPod</application>, <application>gtkpod</application>, and <application>ideviceinstaller</application> for handling multimedia.</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="media-movie-dvd-video">
		<title>Movies, DVDs and videos</title>

		<para>You can watch movies and video clips with the <application>Parole Media Player</application>.</para>

		<section id="media-play-dvd">
			<title>Playing DVDs</title>

			<para>In order to play DVDs you must install some additional software. Unfortunately, DVD support cannot be provided by default in Xubuntu due to legal restrictions in some countries.</para>

			<caution><para>Read <xref linkend="media-video-restricted" /> before following the instructions below. There are some legal issues that you should be aware of.</para></caution>

			<para>To be able to play DVDs, do the following:</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Install the <literal>&package;<ulink url="apt://libdvdnav4">libdvdnav4</ulink></literal>, <literal>&package;<ulink url="apt://libdvdread4">libdvdread4</ulink></literal> and <literal>&package;<ulink url="apt://gstreamer1.0-plugins-ugly">gstreamer1.0-plugins-ugly</ulink></literal> packages.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Insert a DVD into your drive. It should open automatically in the <application>Parole Media Player</application>.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>If you would like to play encrypted DVDs, open &terminal; and type the following into the <application>Terminal</application> followed by the <keycap>&key;Enter</keycap> key: <userinput>sudo apt-get install libdvd-pkg</userinput> Take note of the information provided in the terminal during installation, particularly with regard to upgrades to the package.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para> Once libdvd-pkg is finished run <userinput>sudo dpkg-reconfigure libdvd-pkg</userinput> The installation of libdvdcss2 will now complete.</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>

		<section id="media-play-video">
			<title>Playing video</title>

			<para><application>Parole Media Player</application> supports most video types. If you try to play an unsupported video file, <application>Parole Media Player</application> may notify you of a missing plugin. You can then install this plugin by following the wizard. Afterwards, you may need to restart <application>Parole Media Player</application>.</para>

			<para>If you are having difficulties getting a video to stream in your browser, <application>Parole Media Player</application> supports streaming most types of video. To open a video in <application>Parole Media Player</application>, right-click the video and select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Open with Parole Media Player</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>

			<section id="media-video-restricted">
				<title>Restricted formats</title>

				<para>Some video formats, such as Adobe Flash, QuickTime and Windows Media Video, are proprietary and so support for them cannot be included in Xubuntu by default. You must install some extra software to allow playback.</para>

				<para>In order to play the most common proprietary formats in <application>Parole Media Player</application> or <application>Firefox</application>, install the <literal>&package;<ulink url="apt://xubuntu-restricted-extras">xubuntu-restricted-extras</ulink></literal> package.</para>
			</section>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="media-burning">
		<title>Burning CDs and DVDs</title>

		<para>You can make your own CDs and DVDs by burning files onto a blank disc using the CD or DVD writer drive of your computer.</para>

		<para><application>Xfburn</application> is the default application in Xubuntu to complete these tasks. <application>Xfburn</application> allows you to to easily create audio CDs, burn CDs and DVDs with either plain data or disk images and prepare blank re-writable disks for a new burn.</para>

		<para>In order to launch <application>Xfburn</application>, go to &xfburn;.</para>

		<para>Once launched, you can insert a CD-R(W) or DVD-R(W) you wish to write to and then select the button corresponding to the action you wish to take (<guibutton>New Data Composition</guibutton>, <guibutton>Audio CD</guibutton>, etc.).</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
