<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-common SYSTEM "../../libs-common/xubuntu-common.ent">
%xubuntu-common;
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-user SYSTEM "../libs/xubuntu-user.ent">
%xubuntu-user;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs-common/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
<!ENTITY language "C">
]>
<chapter id="internet-networks">
	<title>Troubleshooting</title>

	<section id="network-troubleshooting">
		<title>Network troubleshooting</title>

		<para>Before attempting any troubleshooting, ensure that the network connections are enabled:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Click the <application>NetworkManager</application> icon in the notification area</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Check <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Enable Networking</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Check <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Enable Wi-Fi</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>If your network connection still doesn't work:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>For wired (Ethernet) connections, please see <xref linkend="network-troubleshooting-general" /></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>For wireless connections, please see both <xref linkend="network-troubleshooting-general" /> and <xref linkend="network-troubleshooting-wireless" /></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>If your network connection problems are still not resolved, see <xref linkend="network-troubleshooting-advanced" /></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<section id="network-troubleshooting-general">
			<title>General troubleshooting</title>

			<para>If your network connection is not working properly, there are a few tools that can be used to help diagnose the problem.</para>

			<section id="network-troubleshooting-information">
				<title>Get information about the current connection</title>

				<para>To get information about your network connection and network devices, you have two options:</para>

				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>Using <application>NetworkManager</application></para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para>Click on the <application>NetworkManager</application> icon</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>Select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Connection Information</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. If this is disabled, it is likely there is no active connection. Try using <application>ifconfig</application> to find out more.</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>Each active connection will have its own tab where you can find relevant connection information</para></listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>	
						<para>Using <application>ifconfig</application></para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para>Open a terminal (&terminal;), type the command <userinput>ifconfig</userinput> then press the <keycap>&key;Enter</keycap> key.</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para><application>ifconfig</application> will show you extensive information about your connection, including logical or connection name(s) (e.g. enp3s0) in the left column, IP address in the <guilabel>inet addr</guilabel> column and the MAC address for your device in the <guilabel>HWaddr</guilabel> column</para></listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</section>

			<section id="network-troubleshooting-working">
				<title>Check if a connection is working properly</title>

				<para>A reliable method to check if a connection is working properly is to ping another computer on the network or the Internet.</para>

				<para>To check if your computer is connected to the Internet, open a terminal (&terminal;), type the command <userinput>ping -c 3 www.xubuntu.org</userinput> then press the <keycap>&key;Enter</keycap> key.</para>

				<para>The computer will then attempt to contact www.xubuntu.org three times and display the results. The ping statistics display the number of packets transmitted, how many packets were received, the percentage of packet loss, and the total time spent.</para>

				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>0% packet loss indicates that your computer is connected to the Internet</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Greater than 0% but less than 100% packet loss indicates that your computer has a poor connection to the Internet or a poor wireless signal</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>100% packet loss indicates that your computer has a very bad connection, or is connected to an access point or router that is not connected to the Internet</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>

				<para>If you get an error message that says "www.xubuntu.org can not be found" or "unknown host", then your computer is probably not connected to the Internet or is unable to reach a Domain Name System (DNS) server.</para>
			</section>
		</section>

		<section id="network-troubleshooting-wireless">
			<title>Wireless troubleshooting</title>

			<para>This section covers some common problems faced with wireless support. There is much more information available in the <ulink url="&communitywiki-wifi;">Community Help Wiki</ulink>.</para>

			<note><para>Please note that the steps in this troubleshooting guide are designed to be carried out in the order shown, unless you are pointed to a different subsection.</para></note>

			<section id="network-troubleshoothing-wifi-on">
				<title>Check that the device is turned on</title>

				<para>Many wireless network devices can be turned on or off. Check for a hardware switch or a keyboard function key to turn the wireless device on.</para>

				<para>If the device is turned on, continue to the next topic.</para>
			</section>

			<section id="network-troubleshooting-device-recognized">
				<title>Check if the device is recognized</title>

				<para>Open a terminal (&terminal;), type the command <userinput>sudo lshw -C network</userinput>, then press the <keycap>&key;Enter</keycap> key. You will see some output, along with the words <guilabel>CLAIMED</guilabel>, <guilabel>UNCLAIMED</guilabel>, <guilabel>ENABLED</guilabel> or <guilabel>DISABLED</guilabel>.</para>

				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para><guilabel>CLAIMED</guilabel> indicates that a driver is loaded but not functioning. Continue to <xref linkend="network-troubleshooting-ndiswrapper" />.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><guilabel>UNCLAIMED</guilabel> indicates that there is no driver loaded. Continue to <xref linkend="network-troubleshooting-ndiswrapper" />.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><guilabel>ENABLED</guilabel> indicates that the driver is installed and working. Continue to section <xref linkend="network-troubleshooting-router" />.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><guilabel>DISABLED</guilabel> indicates the driver is installed, but disabled. Continue to <xref linkend="network-troubleshoothing-wifi-on" />.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</section>

			<section id="network-troubleshooting-ndiswrapper">
				<title>Using Windows wireless drivers</title>

				<para>Xubuntu supports a system known as <application>NDISWrapper</application>. This allows you to use a Windows wireless device driver under Xubuntu. To start using <application>NDISWrapper</application>:</para>

				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>Obtain the Windows driver for your network device and locate the file that ends with <literal>.inf</literal></para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Install the <literal>&package;ndisgtk</literal> package</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Go to &wm-settings-ndisgtk;</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Select <guibutton>Install new driver</guibutton></para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Choose the location of your Windows .inf file and click <guibutton>Install</guibutton></para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton></para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</section>

			<section id="network-troubleshooting-router">
				<title>Checking for a connection to the router</title>

				<para>Open a terminal (&terminal;), type the command <userinput>iwconfig</userinput> then press the <keycap>&key;Enter</keycap> key.</para>

				<para>If the <guilabel>ESSID</guilabel> for your router is displayed, there may be a problem with ACPI support. Boot Xubuntu with the <literal>pci=noacpi</literal> option.</para>
			</section>
		</section>

		<section id="network-troubleshooting-advanced">
			<title>Advanced troubleshooting</title>

			<para>The following troubleshooting methods are a bit more technical. Please try these methods only if the above methods failed.</para>

			<section id="network-troubleshooting-ip-assignment">
				<title>Checking IP assignment</title>

				<para>Open a terminal (&terminal;), type the command <userinput>ifconfig</userinput> then press the <keycap>&key;Enter</keycap> key. If there is an IP address displayed, continue to <xref linkend="network-troubleshooting-dns" />.</para>

				<para>From the terminal enter the following command, replacing <literal>enp3s0</literal> with the name of the connection shown in the output from the <application>ifconfig</application> command: <userinput>sudo dhclient enp3s0</userinput></para>

				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>If you receive a message that says bound to <literal>xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx</literal> continue to <xref linkend="network-troubleshooting-dns" /></para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>If not, reboot the system</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</section>

			<section id="network-troubleshooting-dns">
				<title>Check Domain Name Servers (DNS)</title>

				<para>Open a terminal (&terminal;), type the command <userinput>nmcli device show</userinput> then press the <keycap>&key;Enter</keycap> key.  Look for the entries under <literal>IP4.DNS</literal></para>

				<para>To check if the listed DNS works, open a terminal (&terminal;), type the command <userinput>dig xubuntu.org</userinput> then press the <keycap>&key;Enter</keycap> key.  If you see the word <literal>NOERROR</literal> in the header section of the output, your DNS is working.</para>

				<para>If there are no DNS settings listed, contact your Internet Service Provider (ISP), and find out your primary and secondary domain name servers.</para>
			</section>
		</section>
	</section>

</chapter>
